<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: index | P2 Magazine]]></title>
  <link href="http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/blog/categories/index/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-07T14:35:46+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[The P2 Elves]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[p2@thoughtworks.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Word From The Editor]]></title>
    <link href="http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/issue03/index"/>
    <updated>2013-08-01T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/issue03/index</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I remember working on a project where some team members were dissatisfied with the daily stand-up. They didn’t feel like they were getting any value out  of it. For the next iteration, the team held no stand-ups. During the retrospective, we talked about what information we hadn’t shared with each other that we should have. Stand-up was brought back the following iteration to share just that information.</p>

<p>In the 3rd issue of P2 magazine we pause improve this and ask for feedback on whether it should come back. We talk to Musa Kurhula Baloyi about the challenges of <em>Localisation and Digitisation in Africa</em>. Nick Thorpe continues his series with John Stojanovski and John’s history with computer viruses. Ali Lemer talks to Anette Bergo about her experiences of setting up the MelbJS group. All this, more and some new features like an RSS feed and arrow keys make up the August edition of P2 Magazine.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;d like to get in touch, you can email us at: <a href="&#x6d;&#97;&#x69;&#x6c;&#116;&#111;&#x3a;&#x70;&#50;&#64;&#x74;&#x68;&#x6f;&#117;&#103;&#x68;&#116;&#x77;&#111;&#x72;&#107;&#115;&#46;&#x63;&#111;&#109;">&#112;&#x32;&#64;&#116;&#104;&#x6f;&#117;&#103;&#104;&#116;&#119;&#111;&#114;&#x6b;&#115;&#x2e;&#99;&#x6f;&#x6d;</a></p>

<p>Ryan Boucher, Editor in Chief</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Word From The Editor]]></title>
    <link href="http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/issue02/index"/>
    <updated>2013-07-01T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/issue02/index</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I write this, I’m thinking about the threads that run through this edition of P2. We don’t plan a theme for each edition, but they do emerge. This time there are two: iterative approaches to software development, and personal stories.</p>

<p>The personal stories sometimes bring some sadness with them. When people move on, or move back home, we miss their stories. We’re bringing you some of these stories in this edition. Stories like how John Stojanovski became interested in security, which will become our first ongoing episodic feature. We also talk to Stewart Gleadow about mobile development, and Andrew Carr about design and the NoPSD movement. Welcome to our second issue of P2 Magazine.</p>

<p>Ryan Boucher, Editor in Chief</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Word From The Editor]]></title>
    <link href="http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/issue01/index"/>
    <updated>2013-06-01T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/issue01/index</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to the inaugural issue of P2 Magazine. Pillar 2, within ThoughtWorks, is software excellence, flanked by pillars one and three of sustainable business and social justice. These three equally support ThoughtWorks.</p>

<p>Software excellence evades definition. It’s easy to think of concise lines of code laid out like prose. But we didn’t want this magazine to be exclusively for those who think in code. ThoughtWorks is filled with testers, designers, analysts and innovators. We had to expand our definition to include the excellence that happens before and after we even consider how we solve a problem.</p>

<p>When we embarked on this project in early May, we decided to publish monthly without regard for getting it ‘right’. We’ll release, get feedback, learn, improve and then do it all again. This lightweight: do, learn, adapt is at the core of how ThoughtWorks operates and comes to life in <em>Big Data Ain’t So Big</em> and a new perspective on learning is uncovered by Jen Smith. I tell a cautionary tale and we experiment with <em>Improve This</em> and <em>A Puzzle</em>.</p>

<p>We’ve strived to avoid the middle ground. There are plenty of places on the Internet to find a balanced view. Our stories tell just one side. An opinionated, well written, human story that is interesting, original and, we hope, a conversation starter.</p>

<p>In order to learn, we need feedback. So please tell us what you think: <a href="&#109;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#116;&#x6f;&#58;&#x70;&#x32;&#x40;&#x74;&#x68;&#x6f;&#117;&#x67;&#104;&#x74;&#119;&#111;&#x72;&#107;&#x73;&#x2e;&#99;&#x6f;&#109;">&#112;&#50;&#x40;&#116;&#x68;&#x6f;&#117;&#x67;&#x68;&#x74;&#119;&#x6f;&#114;&#x6b;&#115;&#x2e;&#99;&#111;&#109;</a></p>

<p>Ryan Boucher, Editor in Chief</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
