<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: index | P2 Magazine]]></title>
  <link href="http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/blog/categories/index/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-04T18:15:11-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[The P2 Elves]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[p2@thoughtworks.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Word From The Editor]]></title>
    <link href="http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/issue09/index"/>
    <updated>2014-03-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/issue09/index</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to the March issue of P2.</p>

<p>This month we have a new area of focus in our articles &ndash; hardware. ThoughtWorks has just completed the 100 days of Hardware initiative, which kicked off in North America, but has spread to many of our regions globally. One output of that was TheBot from Bangalore. Karan Misra will share his story this month, but expect more hardware articles in the future.</p>

<p>We also have some more DevOps fun with Vagrant from Derek Hammer.</p>

<p>On the Polyglot front Rouan Wilsenach explains why hiring a polglot programmer is good for your team vs a language expert and Dave Elliman tells us a story of using Clojure on a Java team.</p>

<p>We are very development heavy this month and we want P2 Magazine to encompass all aspects of what ThoughtWorks does and how we innovate and create excellent software. So next month Amira Pettus will join the team to drive through some stories from the UX community. If you would like to contribute stories on Testing, Analysis or Process then please reach out to us on <a href="&#x6d;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#x74;&#111;&#58;&#112;&#x32;&#64;&#116;&#x68;&#111;&#x75;&#x67;&#104;&#116;&#119;&#111;&#x72;&#x6b;&#115;&#x2e;&#x63;&#x6f;&#109;&#46;">&#112;&#50;&#64;&#116;&#x68;&#111;&#x75;&#x67;&#104;&#x74;&#x77;&#111;&#114;&#x6b;&#x73;&#46;&#x63;&#111;&#x6d;&#x2e;</a></p>

<p>Thank you for reading and for the great feedback you&rsquo;ve given the P2 team.</p>

<p>Rachel Laycock, Editor in Chief</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Word From The Editors]]></title>
    <link href="http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/issue08/index"/>
    <updated>2014-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/issue08/index</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to the first P2 for 2014. This is the eighth issue we&rsquo;ve published of the P2 Magazine and the first without the watchful eye of Ryan Boucher at the helm. We have two new elves joining us from across the globe to help us gather stories near you, Rouan Wilsenach in South Africa and Karan Misra in India.</p>

<p>We would love to get more input, so if you would like to contribute send an email to <a href="&#109;&#x61;&#105;&#x6c;&#116;&#111;&#x3a;&#112;&#50;&#x40;&#116;&#104;&#x6f;&#x75;&#x67;&#x68;&#x74;&#119;&#111;&#x72;&#x6b;&#x73;&#46;&#99;&#111;&#x6d;&#46;">&#x70;&#x32;&#x40;&#116;&#x68;&#111;&#117;&#x67;&#104;&#x74;&#119;&#111;&#x72;&#x6b;&#x73;&#x2e;&#x63;&#111;&#109;&#46;</a></p>

<p>This month the Virus and Build Gripes series will take a short hiatus, but they will return with more episodes soon. In the meantime, we hope you enjoy some content from new writers like Mike Vitale who shares his experiences on how to make technical changes at scale in a large organisation or from Sam Gibson on automating your workstation with Babushka. We also have a deep dive on lambdas by the wonderful Neal Ford who will share his thoughts on this.</p>

<p>Thank you for reading and for the great feedback you&rsquo;ve given the P2 team.</p>

<p>Rachel Laycock, Editor in Chief</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Word From The Editors]]></title>
    <link href="http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/issue07/index"/>
    <updated>2013-12-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/issue07/index</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to the final P2 for 2013. In April this magazine wasn&rsquo;t even a glimmer in my eye. This is the seventh issue we&rsquo;ve published since then. It&rsquo;s been hectic at times and yet; fun. I&rsquo;ve learnt a lot about writing and editing having to do it day in and day out.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m off on a 12 month absence at the end of this month. Next year, P2 is back with Rachel Laycock at the helm. Her support is: Sarah Howe, Rebecca Parsons and a host of ThoughtWorkers, possibly even yourself. If you&rsquo;d like to write an article for P2 send an email to <a href="&#x6d;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#116;&#x6f;&#x3a;&#112;&#x32;&#64;&#116;&#104;&#x6f;&#x75;&#103;&#104;&#x74;&#x77;&#x6f;&#x72;&#107;&#x73;&#46;&#x63;&#x6f;&#x6d;">&#112;&#50;&#x40;&#x74;&#104;&#111;&#x75;&#103;&#x68;&#x74;&#x77;&#111;&#x72;&#107;&#115;&#x2e;&#99;&#x6f;&#109;</a></p>

<p>Thank you for reading and for the great feedback you&rsquo;ve given the P2 team over the past seven months.</p>

<p>Ryan Boucher, Editor in Chief</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Word From The Editors]]></title>
    <link href="http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/issue06/index"/>
    <updated>2013-11-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/issue06/index</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to the November issue of P2 Magazine. This month we bring you our biggest issue, and widest variety of authors, to date.</p>

<p>Enjoy,</p>

<p>Ryan Boucher &amp; Rachel Laycock, Editors in Chief</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The October Issue]]></title>
    <link href="http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/issue05/index"/>
    <updated>2013-10-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://thoughtworks.github.io/p2/issue05/index</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to the October issue of P2 Magazine. This issue marks the final one in which I&rsquo;ll be Editor in Chief. The next two issues will see a transition from myself to Rachel Laycock. From next year I&rsquo;ll be away on leave for twelve months.</p>

<p>Ryan Boucher, Editor in Chief</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
